<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vindication of Mr. Bryan Heyns from all the calumnies and reproaches cast upon him by the phanaticks together with a short relation of the present Presbyterian Plot, against the King and government.</title>
            <author>Heyns, Bryan.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95943</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V482</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18923</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895796</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895796</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153714</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95943)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153714)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2375:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vindication of Mr. Bryan Heyns from all the calumnies and reproaches cast upon him by the phanaticks together with a short relation of the present Presbyterian Plot, against the King and government.</title>
                  <author>Heyns, Bryan.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for the author, Brian Heyns, and sold by Walter Davis in Amen-Corner,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXXII. [1682]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Identified as Wing V482, reel 2375, of the UMI microfilm set "Early English books 1641-1700".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C..</note>
                  <note>Identified by ESTC as Wing (CD-ROM, 1996) H1747A.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Heyns, Bryan --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Presbyterianism --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Religion and politics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153714:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153714:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153714:2"/>
            <p>A VINDICATION OF Mr. Bryan Heyns FROM All the Calumnies and Reproaches Caſt upon Him by the PHANATICKS Together with a ſhort RELATION of the <hi>Preſent Presbyterian Plot.</hi> AGAINST THE King and Government.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for the Author, <hi>Bryan Heyns,</hi> and Sold by <hi>Walter Davi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in <hi>Amen-Corner.</hi> MDCLXXXII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:153714:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153714:3"/>
            <head>The EPISTLE to the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have hereunto annexed a Brief account of ſome of the Witneſſes that appear'd againſt me at <hi>Oxford,</hi> when <hi>Colledge</hi> was Try'd, for two reaſons: The <hi>1ſt.</hi> is, I was not able to defend my ſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them there, becauſe I could not preſage who would come to oppoſe me; nor indeed did I regard what any man could ſay in Truth againſt me, to diſparage my ſelf, or extenuate my Evidence; for I never committed that thing in all my life, that I car'd it ſhould be written in my face, unleſs it was to kiſs a Woman. And being asked by ſome Friends, before I went to <hi>Oxford,</hi> whether or no I was ever Guilty of any Crime, to the end I might be fortified to obviate the Adverſaries blaſting my Reputation? I told them then, I would renounce the King's Pardon and Mercy, if any man living could <hi>in foro conſcientiae</hi> ſay, that ever I took the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of a Farthing from any man, feloniouſly or fraudulently, ſince I was born out of my Mothers Womb; nor ever was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any Magiſtrate upon any Felonious or Covinous account, in all my days; ſo that I valued not what any man could ſay againſt me, if he ſpoke the <hi>Naked Truth.</hi> The 2d. reaſon is, the Court where <hi>Colledge</hi> was tryed, was ſo little, and the weather ſo hot, and ſuch a Crowd of People, that the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes for the King were like to be ſtifl'd to Death; ſo that for my part I could not hear what was ſaid againſt me, by any one, but what <hi>John Lun</hi> ſaid, and of him I had a caution be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-hand. Beſides, I did not really believe, that folks who pretend ſo much to the purity of the Goſpel, as the <hi>Whigs</hi> do, would ever ſuborn people to tell Lies in the face of publick
<pb facs="tcp:153714:4"/>Juſtice; for though, as they ſuggeſted, all was falſe that was ſaid againſt <hi>Colledge</hi> then, yet it was no Preſident for ſo Godly a Party to make themſelves ſo great Villains, and Lyars, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any account whatſoever, as to forge Calumnies againſt the Witneſſes. The Primitive Chriſtians when they were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted, were uſed to ſay, that <hi>Preces &amp; Lacrymae ſunt arma Eccleſiae: Tears and Prayers are the Weapons of the Church;</hi> But inſtead of this Attonement to GOD, the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> Weapons are, <hi>Subornation, Perjury, Forgeries, Dethroning and Murthering of Kings.</hi> So even as a certain Author writes, treating of the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of King CHARLES I. in theſe words: <hi>Annus 4<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> parici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium protulit, gentibus omnibuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſeculis execrandum. Horet cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus vel rem deſignare.</hi> In <hi>Engliſh</hi> thus: The <hi>year</hi> 48. <hi>brought forth a Murther, of all Nations to be deteſted; My Pen ſhivers to ſet down the matter,</hi> ſaith mine Author. So let all honeſt men ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor their curſed Actions, in theſe years 80. and 81. eſpecially the Execrable ASSOCIATION lately diſcovered, invented and contrived to Aſſaſſinate the beſt of Princes CHARLES II. Exclude His ROYAL BROTHER, and purſue to Death and Deſtruction all thoſe that would <hi>Oppoſe the Ends thereof;</hi> which if we do, and link together, we ſhall be able to diſſipate the <hi>Phanaticks</hi> Tempeſtuous Fury which hovers over our Heads, with the help of the Omniſcient GOD, who in all Ages deliver'd his Servants from the Jaws of the Devil, and the Rage of their Cruel Enemies; which is the hearty Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>BRYAN HEYNS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Page 3. line 33. for name of prevarication, <hi>r. ſtain of prevarication.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153714:4"/>
            <head>A VINDICATION OF Mr. Bryan Heyns, FROM All the Calumnies and Reproaches Caſt upon Him by the PHANATICKS: Together with a ſhort Relation of the <hi>Preſent Presbyterian Plot.</hi> AGAINST THE KING and Government.</head>
            <p>WIth a great deal of Patience I forbore, and almoſt ſlighted the phrenſical Malice of the <hi>Raging Whigs,</hi> who are not only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to term me a <hi>Papist,</hi> but alſo a <hi>Thief, Burglarer,</hi> &amp;c. Nay, with all the Virulency imaginable, they have printed in all their ſcurrilous Pamphlets, That there was not a Crime in Nature, whereof I was not Culpable, although they can produce no Record of Infamy againſt me. And all theſe Calumnies I paſſed by, for theſe ſubſequent Reaſons:</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe there was no Name to the two firſt Pamphlets, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called, <hi>No Protestant Plot;</hi> ſo that I was to ſeek whom to anſwer.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:153714:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> Secondly, The Author of the third Pamphlet, is ſo Infamous a Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain, viz. <hi>Newgate-Thomas Dangerfield,</hi> that I would not honour him ſo far, as to take the leaſt cognizance of what his<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dangerfield</hi> BURNT in the iland.</note> ſtigmatized Paw ſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led againſt me; And in this I followed the Rule of Law, which ſays, <hi>Semel malus, ſemper praeſumitur malus, in eodem genere mali.</hi> I was really poſſeſſed in my ſoul, that no man of Worth or Conſcience, would give the leaſt atome of credit to what he wrote or ſpoke with his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious<note n="⋆" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dangerfield</hi> compares in: Reproaches to Chriſts, in his Pamphlet dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to Sir <hi>John Moore</hi> Lord Mayor.</note> tongue againſt any man; for a Fellow that was Convicted often by Law, of ſo many Notorious Felonies, and other Crimes, can never lodge Belief (in my judgment) in the Intellect of any ſober or honeſt Chriſtian, although he had a thouſand Pardons: For though a Pardon obliterates <hi>Poenam Culpae,</hi> yet it alters not the intrinſick and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential inclination of a man once depraved; For what a man imbibes in his infancy, and thereof attracts a habit, is not with facility excuſſed, but ſtill there remains a tincture of it, according to that Axiom, <hi>Quo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel eſt imbuta recens, ſervabit odorem testa diu;</hi> unleſs the Reformation be, by a ſupernatural grace, infuſed by God into a rational ſoul, which uſeth often the true Acts of Contrition, and hearty Repentance; but ſuch celeſtial Bliſſes deſcend not by <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Ladder often in this Iron Age, eſpecially to that profligate Scum, of Mankind, <hi>Thomas Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerfield.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And theſe precedent Reaſons, were the ſole Motives wherefore I vili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field <hi>Dangerfield</hi>'s<note n="⋆" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dangerfield</hi> ſtood in the Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lory.</note> Pillory Pamphlet. At laſt I ſaw a ſilly a ſilly Pamphlet, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>The Iriſh Evidence Convicted by their own Oaths,</hi> and ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by pettifogging <hi>William Hetherington;</hi> In which, after this wonted raſcally impudence, he reflects upon <hi>Bryan Heyns,</hi> viz. That <hi>Heyns</hi> was one of the foreſaid Evidences that forſwore himſelf about the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Plot: Therefore <hi>Heyns,</hi> to acquit himſelf of that Reproach, is willing to let the world know, That he never was concerned in the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Plot, not knew more of it, than the Child unborn; neither did he ever know any of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Witneſſes, till he ſaw them here in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don;</hi> nor was he ever a Witneſs in <hi>Ireland</hi> againſt any man; neither does he believe, that any of the ancient <hi>Iriſh</hi> Nobility or Gentry, would hurt a Hair of His Majeſties Head, though they may condole and lament, to no purpoſe, their unparallel'd Oppreſſion, under the late Uſurper's Trayterous Crew, and worſt of Rebels. The Emperour <hi>Adrian,</hi> though a <hi>Pagan,</hi> and none of the beſt Princes, took no notice of this kind of Vice in his Subjects, when actually oppreſſed by his wicked Miniſters of State, whom he truſted to adminiſter Juſtice to his people. 'Tis and old ſaying, <hi>That Loſers have leave to ſpeak;</hi> and if ſo, no Hiſtory either Sacred or Profane, ever made mention of the like oppreſſion, as is done to the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Nation; their Eſtates are given to thoſe that actually fought againſt the King, murdered His Royal Father King <hi>Charles</hi> I. and His Subjects. <hi>In fine,</hi> perpetrated all the Villany under Heaven.</p>
            <p>Pardon me (Reader) for theſe Excurſiions, being touched to the quick, to ſee my Native Countrey planted with <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Traytors, whil'ſt the innocent Natives are famiſhed with hunger and thirſt, being wholly ſhut out from all mercy by the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> in which they hoped to be redeemed.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:153714:5"/>
            <p> To return to our purpoſe: <hi>Heyns</hi> has not been in <hi>Ireland</hi> ſince his Minority but once, about eight years ago, and then ſtayed not two months; ſo that it was impoſſible he could in ſo ſhort a time, come to the knowledge of any deſign the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts had on foot, againſt the King or Government; his Buſineſs then into <hi>Ireland</hi> was about his own pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Concerns, as ſeveral perſons of Honour can teſtifie, if occaſion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires. Moreover, <hi>Heyns</hi> declares before God and the world, he never was bribed by <hi>David Fitz-Gerald,</hi> as <hi>Hetherington</hi> alledges in his ſaid Pamphlet, much leſs managed by him, or any man whatſoever, to ſwear againſt any perſon, living or dead; neither does he imagine <hi>Fitz-Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rald</hi> or <hi>Hetherington,</hi> capacitated to ſuggeſt to him, ſuch plenty of reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Reaſon; for <hi>Heyns</hi> his natural <hi>Genius</hi> was better cultivated, than to borrow from ſuch blundred Fountains; and better principled, than to perjure himſelf through any man's perſuaſions. Had <hi>Heyns</hi> no other reaſon to eſchew <hi>Fitz-Gerald</hi>'s company, but how he brought his own chief Sir <hi>John Fitz-Gerald</hi> to trouble, 'tis a convincing argument to him, he would never be true to a man altogether a ſtranger to him, as <hi>Heyns</hi> was; beſides, he can ſafely vouch, That he has not been in <hi>Fitz-Gerald</hi>'s company one quarter of an hour, ſince <hi>Heyns</hi> has been recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to His Majeſty; And, to ſpeak the truth, <hi>Heyns</hi> has ſo little a kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for him, that he never ſalutes him paſſing by; and in this point, he follows King <hi>James</hi>'s Rule, who was wont to ſay, <hi>He never loved a Dog that bit his own Tail.</hi> And notwithſtanding all theſe lucid demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>Heyns</hi> muſt be managed by <hi>Fitz-Gerald,</hi> becauſe <hi>Hetherington ipſe dixit:</hi> But this, with divers other acervations of Villany, are falſly imputed to <hi>Heyns,</hi> by the peſtiferous <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> that Bane of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, to alleviate their preſent nefarious Conſpiracy againſt the King and Government.</p>
            <p>An whereas <hi>Hetherington</hi> affirms in his lowſie Pamphlet, <hi>That as ſoon as the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury <hi>and</hi> Wilmore <hi>were ſworn against,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>the Evidence were rigged, and had plenty of money in their Pockets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Heyns,</hi> to waſh off that name of Prevarication charged upon him by that lying Varlet, declares, <hi>He never was cloathed upon the King's ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt in his whole life, nor ever received any Bribes; and his Watch and other things which he pawned when he was in the City, he never was able to redeem them ſince he came from thence.</hi> But <hi>Hetherington</hi> takes his norme from the inſipid <hi>Whigs,</hi> who have not ſpared with all acrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to maculate and blaſt <hi>Heyns</hi>'s Reputation, ſince he has been inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental to diſcover their treaſonable Practices: But the offers here a fair Propoſal to all the <hi>Phanatiques</hi> living, That if they can produce any man, that is <hi>bona fide</hi> an honeſt man, and of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> (without compulſion) as by Law eſtabliſhed, which will depoſe upon Oath before the King and Council, That the ſaid <hi>Heyns</hi> was in all his life either Beyond Sea, or in <hi>England,</hi> before any Magiſtrate for any Capital, or ſuppoſed Capital Matter or Crime, onely for the Peace, or before Mr. Secretary <hi>Jenkins,</hi> the day he was apprehended by the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers, or when he endeavour'd with other Priſoners to eſcape from the <hi>Kings-Bench;</hi> he will recant whatever he ſaid, and acknowledge his teſtimony in <hi>publico foro,</hi> to be invalid, and of no efficacy. 'Tis true, ſuch a Raſcal as <hi>John Lunn</hi> may ſwear any thing, to boulſter up
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153714:6"/>the eclipſed Cauſe, who offered at <hi>Oxford,</hi> when <hi>Colledge</hi> was tryed, to take the Sacrament, that he met <hi>Heyns</hi>'s, four days after <hi>Colledge</hi>'s <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramus</hi> at the <hi>Old-Baily,</hi> in the <hi>Darby</hi> Ale-houſe, near the <hi>Ditch-ſide,</hi> in <hi>Fleet-street,</hi> when twenty perſons can teſtifie, that <hi>Heyns</hi> was then, and a great while after cloſe confined in a Meſſenger's houſe by the <hi>Hay-market.</hi> Moreover, this Villain was made a lying, perjured Rogue, in open Court, at <hi>Oxford,</hi> by Mr. <hi>White</hi> the Meſſenger, <hi>vide Colledge</hi>'s <hi>Tryal,</hi> fol. 45. So God infatuates pernicious men, when they undergo wicked deſigns.</p>
            <p>Another Bankrupt Villain of theſe Daemoniſh <hi>Whigs,</hi> by name <hi>John Whaly,</hi> whom <hi>Heyns</hi> ſince arreſted, ſaid alſo at <hi>Oxford, That</hi> Heyns <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to ſteal a Silver Tankard when he was a Priſoner in the</hi> Kings-Bench, <hi>and was therefore ſent by Mr.</hi> Lenthal, <hi>then Marſhal, to the Common Side of the ſaid Bench,</hi> which is the falſeſt and infernalleſt Lye that ever was uttered by Man or Devil, for moſt of the Officers of the <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> can juſtifie, when occaſion requires, that <hi>Heyns</hi> was turned to the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Side,</hi> for offering to eſcape out of the ſaid <hi>Bench.</hi> 'Tis a Paradox that he ſhould never be charged with ſuch a Fact by the ſaid <hi>Whaly,</hi> or any other theſe ſix or ſeven years, whereas <hi>Heyns</hi> never abſconded him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but was publickly to the ſeen every day in the City and Suburbs, where he practiſed: But the Devil, who, <hi>ab origine,</hi> gave life and birth to the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> ſtill governs their hearts and actions, and, as he is the Father of all Miſchief and Lyes, they are by Regeneration his adopted Children in all Vice and Iniquity, witneſs their Rebellions, Murders, Maſſacres, ſtamping of the bleſſed Sacrament of our Saviour's Body under Foot, Sacriledges, Depredations in all parts of<note n="⋆" place="margin">Vide <hi>Dr.</hi> Hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>, Hiſto<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y of the <hi>Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> Printed in 16<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</note>
               <hi>Europe,</hi> from the very commencement of them, to this very day, that it would fill a whole Volume, to ſet down the Particulars of their horrid and bloody Proceedings, inſomuch that the Name of a <hi>Presbyterian</hi> is a ſhame and a ſcandal to Chriſtian Religion. <hi>Hetherington,</hi> the Manager of the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Plot,</hi> who durſt tell ſo many Notorious Lyes before the King and Council, As that he was a Juſtice of Peace about the age of ſixteen years: And like wiſe he told Mr. <hi>Atterbury</hi> the Meſſenger, that he kept his Coach and ſix Horſes, beſides his vaſt annual Revenues in <hi>Ireland,</hi> when effectively he is and was always a Beggar, (though Mr. <hi>Atterbury</hi> out of meer Charity, at that <hi>interim</hi> of time, bought him Cloaths to his Back) will not ſcruple to forge all Untruths to poyſon the King's Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, thinking thereby to ingratiate himſelf with the Factious Party, to the end his mendicant condition may be a little ſupported, being he has ſhipwrack'd his ruſty credit with the Royal Party already, who have put <hi>Remora's</hi> to his pimping under-hand dealings, and anticipated the clandeſtine deſigns of his Brethren in iniquity the <hi>Whigs</hi> againſt them: And all his Allegations againſt Witneſſes, is only to palliate the flagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Machinations he was a hatching againſt the King, the innocent Queen, the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Ormond,</hi> and all his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, of whom he told my ſelf, <hi>The Three Kingdoms would never flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh till they were all Cut off, for they were all Drones</hi> (that was his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion) <hi>which ſucked all the Honey the purer ſort of Bees culled: for,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>the King, with his Miſtreſſes, eats up all the Fat of the Land, and my Lord of</hi> Ormond, <hi>and his Sons, have ingroſſed into their own hands
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153714:6"/>the best part of</hi> Ireland: <hi>But,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>I have almost done their work, by my management of the</hi> Iriſh <hi>Witneſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſtill to give a further teſtimonial of his zeal to the ſinking Cauſe, he incorporates himſelf with the <hi>Whigs,</hi> and offers impudently, in the Face of the Sun, to ſereen their diſloyal Proceedings againſt their Prince, in ſaying, <hi>The</hi> Iriſh <hi>Witneſſes are ſuborned to drop the Popiſh Plot, and fix another upon the Protestants.</hi> I would ask one queſtion of <hi>Hetherington, Whether he knows actually of his own knowledge any</hi> Iriſh <hi>Papiſts that ever wiſhed His Majesty any harm?</hi> If he knows any, he ought to diſcover them, that ſuch peſtiferous Members may be cut off by Juſtice, if not, 'tis an unchriſtian Action to accuſe an innocent Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, upon the bare Surmiſes of a few lecherous <hi>Iriſh</hi> raſcally Prieſts, who have renounced their Functions, and violated their Vows with God, to ſatisfie their Beaſtly Concupiſcence with the Whores of <hi>London.</hi> But <hi>Hetherington</hi>'s main ſcope in ſpattering of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Witneſſes, and herding himſelf with the <hi>Whigs,</hi> is, becauſe he may one day have Repri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals in lieu of his own fictitious Lands, upon my Lord of <hi>Ormond</hi>'s eſtate, when the <hi>Work is effected,</hi> as the <hi>Phanatiques</hi> phraſe it, for they are ſtill ſo inchanted, that they believe the Cauſe will be ſtill <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>piſh</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all oppoſition; and this gratification will be granted him by the Republican Party of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> for his aſſidual and inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatigable care, by endeavouring to extirpate the Family of the <hi>Stuarts,</hi> and their Adherents, and, perhaps, as I have heard him ſay, be remune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated with the honour of being Lord-Lieutenant of <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſo that you may ſee he aims at no ſmall matter, but reſolves to follow the old ſaying, <hi>He violandum est jús regnandi gratia violandum eſt.</hi> But let <hi>Hetherington</hi> and the Factious learn, that our Sovereign's great wiſdom extends as far as His Regal Power; and that His Royal and mature cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpection, has and will obviate the prepoſterous deſigns of thoſe Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious Incendiaries of State, of which His Majeſty never merited the leaſt Diſloyalty, or ill Thought, unleſs it be in graciouſly pardoning of them their black Treaſons and excerable Murder of the Royal Martyr His Father King <hi>Charles</hi> of bleſſed memory, for which deteſtable and crying Sin, they deſerved a total extinguiſhment and deletion. Amongſt all the Divine Graces and Bleſſings beſtowed upon that Sacred Prince, one is, <hi>That Handkerchiefs dipped in his innocent Blood, (ured very often, with a touch thereof, the Kings-Evil;</hi> and this is a certain truth, that his very Enemies cannot impugn or gain-ſay. Truly I may ſay of thoſe Blood-hound Regicides, what the great <hi>Tertullian</hi> pronounced againſt the Sins of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gourorrha,</hi> that <hi>Impiet as illa ignium meruit imbres:</hi> For certainly no man ſince the Creation to this day, ever heard or read, either in Sacred or Profane Hiſtory, that a King, which had three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms devolved to Him, by ſo many Ages and legal Succeſſions, received, Crowned, and Anointed, by the common Suffrage of all His People, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, likewiſe a long while governed, and impartially adminiſtred the Laws, for divers Years, to all His Subjects, ſhould be at length Tryed, and after Sentenced to be Murdered, by a Company of <hi>Rake-kennels,</hi> and <hi>lewd Presbyterians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Had His preſent Majeſty ſerved theſe. <hi>Raſcals</hi> after His Reſtauration, as <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great did. to the <hi>Phanician</hi> Slaves who aſſaſſinated
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153714:7"/>their Maſters, and uſurped the Government, to hang them up all, there would be no Plots this day to diſturb the Nation. Although the old Cavaliers and their Children grumble ſometimes of their hard uſage, ſince His Majeſties Reſtauration, yet we will not ſuffer in <hi>Cromwel</hi>'s Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-Raſcals, to ſpurn againſt our Prince, but we will cover the earth with our ſlain Bodies, (rather than flinch) to ſupport and perpetuate the Rights of the moſt Serene and Ancienteſt Monarch <hi>Charles</hi> II. this day in the Univerſe, and His lawful Heirs and Succeſſors, whoſe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors were Kings of <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Three hundred and odd Years before the Birth of Chriſt, and this glorious Prince is the 11th King of his own Family, as I can prove by an ancient Hiſtory I have by me: Nor will our Loyal hearts ever allow our Sanction of any ſpurious or beſotted Faction, to ſteer the Helm of that Hierarchical Series of Kings. And if our preſent Sovereign were pleaſed to call to mind the Noble Actions of his Grandfather <hi>Henry</hi> IV. King of <hi>France,</hi> who ſpared nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Civilities nor Careſſes to Gentlemen who ſerved Him well, he could ſtill find Friends enough to eſpouſe His Royal Cauſe, and eaſily al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay the Pride of His Rebellious Subjects. 'Tis reported of that Heroick Prince <hi>Henry</hi> IV. that after he was Crowned King of <hi>France,</hi> he was wont to ſay theſe obliging words to thoſe that fought for him, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſerved him, <hi>That it was great reaſon they ſhould partake of his Feaſt, ſince they ſerved ſo well at his Nuptials with</hi> France. 'Tis alſo recorded of the ſame Prince, <hi>That his very Enemies the Papiſts, had more confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in his Word alone, than in the Writings of others.</hi> Thus the prudent man never walks, but by ways ſtrait and virtuous; the cunning, on the contrary, by paths oblique and wicked. The prudent cannot but be generous and good, whil'ſt the other cannot be but baſe, deceitful and unworthy.</p>
            <p>To return to our purpoſe: As for my part, I call God to Witneſs, <hi>There is no King in the world I love better than</hi> Charles <hi>II. nor no Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment under the Sun I love ſo well as Kingly Government.</hi> 'Tis true, I was diſcontented, becauſe my Father's Eſtate was given to others, without the leaſt colour of Juſtice, and he in his old days miſerable, and in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream want; he and his Anceſtors were always Loyal to the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> and the himſelf was a Priſoner whil'ſt His Majeſty was in Exile, for adhering to the Marquis of <hi>Clanricard,</hi> His Majeſties Lord-Deputy in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas 'tis reported by ill-affected perſons, That his ancient Eſtate, or what Lands he pretends too, was but 40 <hi>l. per annum;</hi> 'tis the falſeſt Lye that ever was ſpoke by any man: For what he had in his own poſſeſſion before the late Wars, beſides ſeveral Reverſions that fell to him ſince, by his Birth-right, if he could have the benefit of them, or any other of his Pretenſions, I will maintain is above 400 <hi>l. per annum</hi> at this inſtant. If any queſtions the reality of this Aſſertion, he may have an account by the Poſt from the Auditor-General's Office in <hi>Dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin,</hi> where he ſhall ſee inrolled a Patent in <hi>Hughboy-Heyns,</hi> of <hi>Leidigane</hi> his name, and how he held his Lands of the Crown by Knights-Service This is no Oſtentation, or Vain-glory, but what I am compelled to write by the Laws of Nature, and common Juſtice, to releaſe my Family (who can vie in Blood or Deſcent with any in <hi>Ireland,</hi> though not in Eſtate,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153714:7"/>or borrow'd Honour) from the waſpiſh tongues of thoſe , who ſtudied with all amaritude to ſpatter me and my Anceſtors, for my Loyalty to my Prince.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hetherington</hi> ſays in his ſcurrilous Pamphlet, <hi>That the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes herded themſelves with theſe tainted</hi> Iriſh Cattle. I would have the Vagabond Beggar learn to diſtinguiſh betwixt his infamous Raſcals which he picked out of all the Gaols in the North of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the ancient <hi>Iriſh</hi> Gentry, who never were contaminated or reputed baſe, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til thoſe Rake-kennels of <hi>Oliver</hi>'s Fellow-Brewers, Tinkers, Coblers, Sweep-Chimneys, Carr-men, and Jakes-men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were all planted in <hi>Ireland.</hi> Theſe ſordid and dunghil Mechanicks inſtructed and ſemina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted amongſt the <hi>Iriſh</hi> all Vice and Wickedneſs, ſo that inſtead of the Virtue and good Nature that was in the ancient Natives, theſe foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Ruſcals have taught them Diſobedience, and all manner of Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. Sure I am, the moſt profound and learned, both in Goſpel, Law, and Hiſtory of the Noble <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, and formerly no ill Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ancient <hi>Iriſh,</hi> when they celebrated their <hi>Encomiums</hi> to Poſterity in their famous Writings, witneſs my L. <hi>Cook</hi> in his 4th <hi>Inſtitutes,</hi> fol. 349. <hi>For-I have</hi> (ſays he) <hi>been informed by many of them that had Judicial places there, and partly of mine own knowledge, that there is no Nation in the Chriſtian world, that are greater lovers of Justice than they are, which virtue muſt of neceſſity be accompanied with many others; and beſides, they are deſcended of the ancient</hi> Britains, <hi>and therefore the more endeared to us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Likewiſe Cambden,</hi> fol. 370. <hi>Patricii diſcipuli tantos progreſſus in re Christiana fecerunt, ut ſubſequenti aetate, Ribernia ſanctorum Patria dice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur, &amp; Scoticts in Hibernia &amp; Britannia Monachis, nihil ſanctius, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil eruditius fuerit, &amp; in univerſam Europam ſanctiſſimorum virorum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amina miſcrint.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Jocelinus Anglus in vita ſancti Patricii, fol. 191. <hi>Ita ut Hibernia ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciali nomine inſula ſanctorum ubique terrdrum jure nominaretur, &amp; paulo poſt, it a ut exteras atque longinquas regiones illuſtrarent verbo ac religionis exemplo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The extraordinary Merits and Loyalty of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Nation, was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in open Parliament, 27. <hi>July</hi> 1660. by our moſt Gracious Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign <hi>Charles</hi> II. touching the Act of Indempnity in theſe words:
<q>I hope I need my nothing of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and that they alone ſhall not be without the benefit of My Mercy; they have ſhewed much Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to Me abroad, and you will have a care of my Honour, and what I promiſed them.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And another time His Majeſty is pleaſed to own their Loyalty in His Declaration in theſe words:
<q>And in the firſt place, We did and muſt always remember, the great Affection a conſiderable party of that Nation expreſſed to Us, during the time of Our being Beyond the Seas, when with all Chearfu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Obedience they received and ſubmitted to Our Orders, and betook themſelves to that Service which We directed, as moſt conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient and behooveful at that time to Us, though attended with incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency enough to themſelves: Which demeanor of theirs, cannot but be thought very worthy of Our Protection, Juſtice and Favor.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:153714:8"/>
            <p> Here I could quote the Authority of many other ancient Authors, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides our preſent Sovereigns moſt Gracious and Royal words in extolling the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Nation; but this taſte ſhall ſuffice, to let all rational men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the good opinion the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> in former Ages. And that the defection of Virtue in ſome few <hi>Iriſh,</hi> had its emanation from the <hi>Engliſh Whigs</hi> planted in <hi>Ireland</hi> ſince 1641, is moſt apparent and perſpicuous by the ſaid Authorities before cited.</p>
            <p>Thus the <hi>Phanaticks</hi> condemn the <hi>Iriſh</hi> for their Loyalty, for 'tis a common ſaying with them, <hi>That none will ſide with the King, but a Rogue or a Papiſt.</hi> Here you may ſee how they crucifie Virtue, and countenance Vice; they hold Loyalty a Crime, and Treaſon worthy of Reward and Applauſe. Such mungrel Raſcals as <hi>Petherington</hi> have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſcandalized the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Nation, who underſtands neither Honour nor Learning, or the Principles of a true Moraliſt that ſays, <hi>Eſt act us fortitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinis more pro Patria:</hi> 'Tis the greateſt Valor in the world to dye for the good of ones Countrey. And although he breathed his firſt Air in <hi>Ireland,</hi> he is like the Moths or Caterpillary, that deſtroy that gives them their Being; or like the Snake, that would infect the Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and his whole houſe that ſaved his life a little before from periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Snow. There is no <hi>Engliſh Whig</hi> that maliciouſly reflects up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the tranſactions of the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> if he will retroſpect and ruminate ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly what inteſtine Wars and broils the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> created in theſe three Kingdoms, and how their trayterous and murderous Actions of the Beſt of King and His Subjects, renders them infamous and odious to God and man, he can ſay but very little againſt the <hi>Iriſh.</hi> I have ſeen a learned Treatiſe in <hi>Latine,</hi> proving the neceſſity of that War raiſed by the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> having begun it in their own defence, to prevent the general ruine and deſtruction deſigned againſt the Kingdom and themſelves, by the beggarly <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Party, that reſolved to thruſt them out of home and houſe, for no other reaſon, but becauſe they were <hi>Papiſts.</hi> Yet I will never vindicate any Subject that flies to Arms, or to any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Hoſtile Commotion, upon any ſpecious pretences whatſoever, without his Princes Commiſſion or Power; for according to St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Rule, <hi>We must not commit evil, that good may come thereof;</hi> but we ought to ſubmit in every thing to our Superiors, and not be Judges of our own Cauſe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebellion is more excuſable than that of the <hi>Engliſh Whigs,</hi> who had no colour to invade the Prerogatives of their. Prince, not Elective <hi>ad nutum populi,</hi> but Succeſſive by many Ages, and that eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by all the fundamental Laws of <hi>England.</hi> And whoſoever will but read that learned and pious Work <hi>Icon Baſilikè,</hi> of King <hi>Charles</hi> I. where he writes of the Rebellion of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and ſeiriouſly balances the occaſion, of their raiſing in that Kingdom, can never harbour ſuch ill thoughts of the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> as is ſpread abroad of them, by their conſtant Enemies the <hi>Whigs.</hi> And that Royal Martyr having a deep ſenſe of the daily Injuſtice done to that Nation, by thoſe who thirſted after <hi>Iriſh</hi> mens Eſtates, more than the ſettlement of a Peace and Unity, writes of that Rebellion in theſe words following:</p>
            <p>
               <q>And certainly, 'tis thought by many wiſe men, that the preposterous Rigour, and unreaſonable Severity, which ſome men carried before them
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153714:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>in <hi>England,</hi> was not the leaſt Incontive, that kindled, and blew up into thoſe horrid flames, the ſparks of diſcontent, which wanted not prediſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Fewel for Rebellion in <hi>Ireland;</hi> where deſpair being added to their former diſcontent, and the fear of future extirpation to their wonted op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, it was eaſie to provoke to an open Rebellion, a People prone enough, to break out to all exerbitant violence, both by ſome Prinicples of their Religion, and the natural deſires of liberty; both to exempt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from their preſent. Restraints, and to prevent thoſe After rigours, wherewith they ſaw themſelves apparently threatned, by the covetous Zeal and uncharitable Tury of ſome men, who think it a great argument of the truth of their Religion, to endure no other but their own.</q>
            </p>
            <p>In another place, the ſame Royal Martyr ſays, (treating ſtill of the ſame Rebellion) <q>That Men are more greedy, to kill the Bear for his skin, than for any harm be hath done. The confiſcation of Mens Eſtates being more beneficial, than the charity of ſaving their Lives, or reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Errors.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And thus this Wiſe and moſt Chriſtian Prince, conſidered the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannical Uſuage, of the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> under thoſe helliſh Fiends, the <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> who, in thoſe days, governed <hi>Ireland,</hi> and forced the Natives to Rebel, of purpoſe to get their Eſtates, as we afterwards ſaw by woful experience.</p>
            <p>The Emperour <hi>Honorius</hi> was of the ſame Sentiment with our Royal. Martyr, the ſaid <hi>Honorius</hi> having diſcover'd the treaſonable practices of <hi>Eucherlus</hi> againſt himſelf and his Empire, told the ſaid <hi>Eucherius</hi> as follows: <hi>Three ſorts of Traytors are to be conſidered</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>by the Sovereign Prince,</hi> viz. <hi>He that commits Treaſon out of Diſcontent, or Injury done him, is pardonable. He that acts Treaſon out of madneſs, is to be pitied. And finally, He that perpetrates Treaſon</hi> ex dominand libidine, <hi>ought to feel the keenneſs of the Axe; for,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>Enſe recidendum eſt, immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabile Vulnus:</hi> Which laſt Sentence I wiſh His Majeſty would put in execution, againſt all thoſe that thirſt after Democracy, for no other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducement or provocation, but becauſe they themſelves would Rule all. I would expoſe my Body to the flames of the moſt violent Fire (like that gallant Roman <hi>Mucius Scaevola</hi>) upon condition that His Majeſty would make an Edict, That all that ſerved under the late Uſurper, or were Authors of the late Rebellion in Forty One, might be baniſhed out of the Three Kingdoms, or ſtigmatized in the Forehead, to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh them from the King's liege people; then every honeſt man could ſit under his own Vine, and our King live in his Throne with Honour, Tranquility, Peace and Plenty, hourly enjoying the Fruition of the hearts and affections of His Loyal Subjects, until is pleaſed the Almighty to call Him to Himſelf, and crown Him with immortal Glory.</p>
            <p>Let the <hi>Whigs,</hi> with all laudable Apology, ſhroud their oblique Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſactions, and preſent Conſpiracy againſt the King, and Government, and pretend to all the Loyalty and Innocency in nature, none will believe them, that has the leaſt ſpark of reaſon; for, to my certain knowledge, they have been a plotting theſe many years, to plant a Commonwealth in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c. And this is eaſily made manifeſt, by their frequent Libelling againſt His Majeſty; by criminating Him of Inceſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:153714:9"/>with the Dutcheſs of <hi>P—,</hi> intimating that ſhe was the Earl of st. <hi>Alban</hi>'s Daughter, by the late Queen-mother of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another Libel I ſaw, reflecting upon the King's Natural Children: That His Majeſty had Fifty five Royal Baſtards, Boys and Girls, beſides thoſe that were in the Panniers: That theſe, in time, would devour the Three Kingdoms, unleſs they were all knocked in the Head: That it was a deed of Charity to cruſh the old Serpent, meaning the King, leſt He would fill the Land with His Lecherous Brood. They have not ſpared His very Effigies or Statue that is ſet up in the <hi>Stocks Market,</hi> to Libel againſt; and the other Effigies of the old King, ſet up at <hi>Charing-Croſs,</hi> and this Libel was called, <hi>The Speech between the Two Horſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another of theſe Libels I ſaw, where the Duke of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades the King to Rule all by His own Great Will; for it was a Mickle Shame for Majeſty to be controuled by ſuch prating Loons, as were Members of the Houſe of Commons.</p>
            <p>Another of His Majeſties Cabinet-Council, in the ſaid Libel, deſires the King to embrace the Mother-Church, viz. <hi>Rome,</hi> and deſtroy all the Hereticks in one Night, as they were at <hi>Paris;</hi> and then His Holy Father the Pope would Canonize Him a Saint, for rooting out the Enemies of God, and the Catholique Church: For as the Pope gave <hi>Henry</hi> VIII, the Title of <hi>Defenſor Fidei,</hi> ſo it was given to this King ſince His Reſtauration, as the ſaid Libel ſets forth, the Title of <hi>Restau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator Eccleſiae Catholicae, &amp; habuit tranſmiſſum and illum, Gladium Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictum, ad extirpandos &amp; expellendes Haereticos:</hi> Theſe are the very words of the Pamphlet.</p>
            <p>Moreover, That it was the worſt thing that ever the Parliament did, to ſettle the Militia upon His Majeſty; yet <hi>Charles</hi> could not live long, becauſe His whole maſs of Blood was all corrupted in His Body, as ſome of His own Phyſicians related to the <hi>Whigs.</hi> That Nature was all conſumed in Him, only conſerved for ſome interval of time, by high Cordials: But if He were once dead, farewel then for ever Kings of <hi>England.</hi> And unleſs the People could have their Ends by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they would hire ſome of the King<hi>'s</hi> Phyſicians, that would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter Him a Powder, or ſome Poyſonous Doſe, (when He ſhould fall into any Fit of Apoplexy) of the ſame Nature, with that, which put a period to King <hi>James</hi>'s days: Being the Guards and Militia could not be taken from Him.</p>
            <p>Other Pamphlets I have ſeen, one whereof was ſo Satyrical and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious againſt <hi>Henry</hi> VII. <hi>Owen Teusder,</hi> his Grandfather, and all the <hi>Welch,</hi> that nothing could be more venomous. The other was againſt King <hi>James,</hi> and the <hi>Scotch</hi> Nation; and what a great Vilification it was to the lofty hearts of <hi>Engliſh</hi> men, to ſloop to <hi>Welch</hi> and <hi>Scotch</hi> Beggars to reign over <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. Theſe two laſt Pamphlets were the ſenecalleſt and odiouſeſt, that ever were penned by man, inſomuch that Nature it ſelf would even bluſh, to give the leaſt auſcultation, to the peruſal of any thing, ſpecified or included in them. The perſon that cauſed the Sandals, Crucifix, and Beads, ſeveral years ago, to be fixed to Mr. Speaker's Chair, in the Houſe of Commons, knew all the forementioned Pamphlets.</p>
            <p>In this Epitome (Reader) you may ſee, as in a tranſparent Glaſs,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153714:9"/>the Phanatiques hearts, by their exterior Deportments, and Overt Facts; for <hi>qualis arbor, talis fructus;</hi> ſuch is the Tree, ſuch is the Fruit; <hi>Et qualis vir, talis oratio;</hi> ſuch is the man, ſuch is his talk. The <hi>Whigs</hi> ſement Treaſon in obſcurity, and when it is ripe, and ready to be acted, it is gilded over with the Cloak of Religion, Liberty and Property: So when they determine to murder Princes, it muſt not be as <hi>Raviliac</hi> or the <hi>Jacobin</hi> privately that murdered two<note n="*" place="margin">Henry <hi>III. &amp;</hi> Henry <hi>IV.</hi>
               </note> Kings of <hi>France,</hi> but publickly, by common ſeeming Juſtice. Here I offer every loyal heart, to give a compendious Relation of the deſign of theſe <hi>Stygian</hi> Raſcals againſt Church and State, and their conſtant malice to imbaſe all honeſt and loyal Subjects, to their King and Countrey. St. <hi>John Damaſcenus</hi> writes, That <hi>in exordio naſcontis Eccleſiae, unicum crat cor, una anima, &amp; una ſententia:</hi> And if all honeſt Subjects, and true Church of <hi>England</hi> men, would be of one Heart, of one Mind, and one Opinion, as the primitive Chriſtians were, the <hi>Whigs</hi> might be eaſily ſcatter'd like duſt in <hi>March.</hi> The <hi>Arians</hi> were more numerous and more learned than every they were, or are at preſent in theſe Three Kingdoms; yet the Orthodox Chriſtians, by their Concatenation and pious Union to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, ſoon ſuppreſſed and diſſipated thoſe contagious Hereticks, and common Incendaries of Mankind.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore join our hearts and hands together againſt theſe cankerous Vermine, to defend our Religion as by Law eſtabliſhed, and our Sovereign's Rights, hoping that God may infuſe into His Royal Heart, in due ſeaſon, to reward His Loyal Subjects, and chaſtize Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious Villains, who thirſt after His Blood, as they did His Fathers: So he that does not wiſh <hi>CHARLES</hi> II. our dread Sovereign, the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity of <hi>David,</hi> the Wiſdom of <hi>Solomon,</hi> the Years of <hi>Nestor,</hi> the Wealth of <hi>Croeſus,</hi> the Glories, Trophies, Lawrels and Triumphs of <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar;</hi> That God may confound his Devices, and his Name be razed out of the Book of Life, and Memory of Future Ages:</p>
            <closer>Which is the daily Prayer of <signed>B. HEYNS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>IN the 29<hi rend="sup">t</hi>h Page of the <hi>Second Part of No-Proteſtant-Plot,</hi> there it is inſerted, That <hi>Perſonae vili non facile creditur,</hi> ſaith the Civil Law, A Beggarly or Baſe Fellow is not to be credited. Such an one, ſaith the Author, <hi>Quem fames, magis quam faima incitat,</hi> whom Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and Want have greater power over, than reſpect to Reputation, is not to be hearken'd unto what he ſays. Surely the Scribler of the ſaid Pamphlet, was ſome what intoxicated when he wrote that Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph, otherwiſe he never conſider'd how all men knew <hi>T— O—</hi> to have begged of <hi>Pickering</hi> for Crums of Bread at <hi>Somerſet-houſe:</hi> Beſides, that he was a common Beggar, amongſt the Roman Catholiques;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153714:10"/>for ſome Years, is an undeniable matter of Fact, that none dare contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict. And how <hi>D—ld</hi> was in moſt Gaols of the Kingdom, for Pilfering, Cheating, and Stealing, all <hi>England</hi> knows: Yet what theſe beggarly and infamous Scoundrels ſwear, though it be as falſe as God is true, muſt be Goſpel, becauſe they ſwear for the people of God, <hi>per antiphraſin</hi> the Devils.</p>
            <p>Did not <hi>O—</hi> ſwear that he gave a Commiſſion to Sir <hi>Francis Rat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliffe</hi> in <hi>Wild-houſe</hi> Garden, when divers perſons of Quality did teſtifie before the King and Council, that Sir <hi>Francis</hi> was not in <hi>London</hi> four years before: And when <hi>O—</hi> ſaw him, he knew him not, though the pretended Commiſſion was but given to Sir <hi>Francis</hi> by <hi>O—</hi> himſelf, a little before he diſcover'd the Plot, as <hi>O—</hi> pretended.</p>
            <p>Did not the ſame <hi>O—</hi> ſwear againſt one Mr. <hi>Preſton,</hi> that he was a Prieſt, and heard <hi>O—</hi>'s Confeſſion in <hi>Wild-houſe;</hi> though all the Maſters of the Pariſh knew <hi>Preſton</hi> to be a married man, that lived in <hi>Duke-ſtreet</hi> for many years, and paid all Pariſh-duties. A Lye ſo abſurd in it ſelf, and ſo excentrical to common Reaſon, that the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador, who always keeps a Catalogue of all the Prieſts in his Houſe, (for fear of any Abuſe or Scandal in Proteſtant Countries) would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low a man that was publickly known to have a Wife and Children, to celebrate Divine Service in his Chappel; whereas if the leaſt informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion were made againſt him to the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> for permitting ſuch ſacrilegious Actions to be done in his ſaid Chappel, he incurred not only the danger of Excommunication, but alſo the loſs of his life, if ever he went home. And this all men can witneſs to be true, that knows the Canons and Conſtitutions of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church. The ſaid <hi>Preston</hi> was kept two years and above a Priſoner in <hi>Newgate</hi> till he was run'd; and when his Wife brought the Chief of the Pariſh, to prove <hi>Preſton</hi> was no Prieſt, before the Houſe of Lords at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Plot, a certain Noble Lord over-ruled all things, and would not allow <hi>O—</hi> to be made a Lyar in ſuch a High Court of Juſtice, leſt the Son of <hi>Belial</hi>'s Forgery might be detected, and conſequently the <hi>Achitophelian</hi> Plot fruſtrated.</p>
            <p>An infinite number of other Lyes I could here ſet down, but theſe two ſhall ſuffice, to prove the Saviour of the Nation, (to wit <hi>O—</hi>) not to be exempted from the number of perjured Villains.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Third Part</hi> of the <hi>No-Proteſtant-Plot,</hi> pag. 87, the crude and fooliſh lying Scribler thereof, thunders forth againſt <hi>Heyns,</hi> all the <hi>Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingſgate</hi> Language that his black and filthy Soul can breathe out of his polluted lips; but becauſe <hi>Heyns</hi> does not know what Spawn of a Dunghil it is, he will retaliate the Sycophant-Slave withe ſame Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage as he gives.</p>
            <p>And whereas the Varlet charges <hi>Heyns</hi> in his ſaid Treaſonable Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet, to be a Witneſs in ſome matters betwixt Major <hi>Bill,</hi> and my Lady <hi>Windham,</hi> the Hangman is not only a Lyar in this Point, but in all other Particulars; for <hi>Heyns</hi> was never a Witneſs betwixt Major <hi>Bill,</hi> and my Lady <hi>Windham,</hi> in his whole Life, nor ever for, or againſt any man upon Oath, onely the Depoſition he made before Sir <hi>George Treby,</hi> touching the Earl of <hi>Shaſtsbury,</hi> till he appeared againſt <hi>Colledge,</hi> and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153714:10"/>the reſt of that Gang. 'Tis true, <hi>Heyns</hi> call'd my Lady <hi>Windham</hi> Whore, by reaſon of ſome difference that happened; whereupon ſhe arreſted him, and when he was too hard for her, and all the Judges of the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> and others, againſt her, for her idle ways, ſhe got an <hi>Affidavit</hi> man, that ſwore <hi>Heyns</hi> ſhould ſay, <hi>She was my Lord-Chief-Juſtice</hi> Rainſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford<hi>'s Whore; and becauſe for Age he could not act with her, that ſhe Frigged him.</hi> Which ſo incenſed the old Gentleman againſt <hi>Heyns,</hi> that he ordered him to be kept a cloſe Priſoner in the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> until my Lady and <hi>Heyns</hi> were reconciled, and drunk a Bottle of Burnt Brandy together; and this is the truth of that ſtory about my Lady <hi>Windham,</hi> as an hundred Perſons can teſtifie, if occaſion requires.</p>
            <p>The next Lye the Pimp frames in his ſaid Pamphlet, is about my Lord Chief-Juſtice <hi>Pemborton,</hi> that <hi>Heyns</hi> ſhould ſwear at <hi>Colledge</hi>'s Tryal, <hi>That in</hi> March <hi>laſt</hi> Colledge <hi>did rail against my Lord Chief-Juſtice Pemberton;</hi> when he was not at all Chief-Juſtice, nor no thoughts thereof. <hi>Heyns</hi> anſwer'd that Point ſo well once before, that he thought he put an end to the <hi>Whiggiſh</hi> Tautologies; for when mention was made of my Lord Chief-Juſtice <hi>Pemberton</hi> in <hi>Colledge</hi>'s Tryal at <hi>Oxford, Heyns</hi> never named any particular month, time or place, in relation to Sir <hi>Francis Pemberton;</hi> for if there had been any ſuch Query demanded of him, he could eaſily anſwer, That <hi>Colledge</hi> ſpoke ill of my Lord Chief-Juſtice <hi>Pemberton</hi> divers times, and eſpecially in his own houſe, before Mrs. <hi>Fitz-Harris,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Ivy;</hi> nay, if need requires, an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Citizen of <hi>London</hi> will be produced, that can verifie that <hi>Colledge</hi> called Sir <hi>Francis Pemberton</hi> a thouſand Rogues, and that he hoped the next Parliament that ſate, would hang him up, becauſe he gave his opinion to the King, that <hi>Fitz-Harris</hi> might be tryed out of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>And for <hi>Heyns</hi> being married to one Mrs. <hi>Mansfield,</hi> (as is alledged in the ſaid Pamphlet) 'tis ſuch Non-ſenſe that none but a fooliſh ſimple <hi>Whig,</hi> would publiſh ſuch a ridiculous Story, for the Gentlewoman her ſelf denies ſhe ever ſpoke any ſuch thing. If any be curious to know the truth of this falſe Alarum,-Mrs. <hi>Mansfield</hi> lodges at the <hi>Twiſted Poſts,</hi> in <hi>James-ſtreet</hi> in <hi>Covent-garden,</hi> who will certifie him of the truth of things. But 'tis no marvel the Phanatiques will ſix two Marriages upon <hi>Heyns</hi> at once, when they impoſe two upon His Majeſty, <hi>viz.</hi> that He was married to the Duke of <hi>Monmouth</hi>'s mother,<note place="margin">Horrid Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to His Sacred Majeſty.</note> although he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied it upon the word of a Chriſtian, and a King.</p>
            <p>Another idle Fable is ſet down in the ſaid Pamphlet of Mr. <hi>Heyns,</hi> how he counterfeited a Letter from one Mr. <hi>Oliver,</hi> a Priſoner in the <hi>Fleet-Priſon,</hi> to one Mr. <hi>Harbottle</hi> of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> whereby Mr. <hi>Oliver</hi> was cozen'd of the value of 200 <hi>l. Heyns</hi> anſwered this <hi>Whiggiſh Lye</hi> once before, and had it printed in Mr. <hi>Thompſon</hi>'s Intelligence. But I leave it to the judgment of any rational man, how the ſaid <hi>Oliver</hi> could be cheated of 200 <hi>l.</hi> having ſworn himſelf out of Priſon, not to be worth 10 <hi>l.</hi> in all the World, by the laſt Act of Parliament made three or four years ago, for the Releaſe of poor Priſoners for Debt, Beſides, the Statute of Bankrupt was extended upon all his real and perſonal Eſtate, many years before <hi>Heyns</hi> ever knew him, and Mr. <hi>Adams</hi> that lives in <hi>Holborn,</hi> a Barriſter of <hi>Lincolns-Inn,</hi> was one of the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:153714:11"/>for the ſaid Statute of Bankrupt; moreover, <hi>Heyns</hi> calls God to witneſs, he never knew Mr. <hi>Harbottle</hi> in all his life. Some few things more I have to anſwer, that are publiſhed in the ſaid Pamphlet. One is, that it was beneath the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> to ſpeak to ſuch a <hi>mean Raſcal</hi> as <hi>Heyns</hi> is, or words to that effect. Of this Pamphleteer, I would ask theſe two Queſtions, What does he conceive by theſe word, <hi>mean Raſcal?</hi> If he intimates <hi>Heyns</hi> baſeneſs of Birth, he can eaſily prove himſelf as well born, by Father and Mother, as the Noble Peer, ſetting aſide the King's Impreſſion of Honour; his Father is deſcended from the ancient Family of the <hi>Heyns</hi> of <hi>Connaught,</hi> originally ſprung from a younger Son of <hi>Miletin<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> that was Monarch of <hi>Ireland.</hi> And in <hi>Henry</hi> the VIII's Reign, his Anceſtor by the Father, ſide, had power of Life and Death upon his own Eſtate, and had Fifty Mannors that were his real Inheritance. His Family was always Loyal to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> ſo that he will put his Life to iſſue, if ever, there was a Traytor of his own Line.</p>
            <p>His Mother was deſcended of the Noble and Ancient Family of the <hi>Burks</hi> of <hi>Clanricarde,</hi> that have been Peers of <hi>England,</hi> and are ſtill Peers of <hi>Ireland.</hi> The Royal Houſe of <hi>Lancaſter</hi> married the onely Heireſs and Daughter of the Earl of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lster</hi> and <hi>Clanricarde,</hi> whoſe name was <hi>Burke,</hi> the Title of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter</hi> being given to the ſole Heirs of his Body, lawfully begotten, and in her Right the Duke of <hi>York</hi> by the <hi>Lancaſter</hi> Line, is Hereditary Earl of the ſaid Province. In all Ages the ſaid Family of the <hi>Burkes</hi> have ſhewed their Loyalty to the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> and kept the Crown of <hi>Ireland</hi> upon Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s head, having with unſpeakable Fortitude and true Valor, defeated the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and <hi>Spaniards,</hi> in ſeveral pitched Battels, when the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> invaded <hi>Ireland</hi> in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Reign.</p>
            <p>If he means that <hi>Heyns</hi> was Baſely Educated, the Pamphleteer will be laughed at; for no private Gentleman's Son could have better Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuments inſtilled into him, than he had in thoſe liberal Sciences imbel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing a Gentleman. Beſides, he lived always by his own honeſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, and independant of any man, which ſeveral <hi>Whigs</hi> in <hi>London</hi> can witneſs. It was his Fathers Loyalty to his Prince, that clouded his Birth and Breeding; for had he ſided with the late Uſurper, he might enjoy his own Inheritance to this day. Let no man imagine, that I pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh theſe things of my Family, out of Vain-glory, but to let the world know, I want nothing to make me a complete Gentleman, but an Eſtate, and that I am not ſuch an abject perſon as the <hi>Whigs</hi> render me to the world. Beſides, I think I do my Prince a great deal of Juſtice, in clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my Reputation from thoſe Aſperſions daily ſpoke of me by his Enemies</p>
            <p>And whereas 'tis printed in the ſaid Pamphlet, that it was altogether groundleſs, what <hi>Heyns</hi> depoſed againſt the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> relating to the Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> viz. <hi>That his Mother was not deſcended of the Plantagenets. Heyns</hi> deſires the Reader to conſult the Heralds, who are ready to prove that ſhe was deſcended of a Siſter or Daughter to <hi>Edw.</hi> IV. But the Pamphleteer may as well deny this point, as that the Noble Peer never ſpoke to <hi>Heyns.</hi> And I do really believe the Earl
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:153714:11"/>of <hi>S—y</hi> would not involve his Native Countrey in a Civil War, as 'tis there mentioned, out of any love he had for the Duke of <hi>Bucks,</hi> but out of that odium he bears to the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> and others, he would make a <hi>New Aſſociation,</hi> with the Infernal Fiends, and offer all things that are dear to him in this Life, as a libation to the Devil, upon condition he might revenge himſelf upon the <hi>Yorkists.</hi> And whereas the ſaid Pamphlet denies that the Earl of <hi>Sh.</hi> ſpoke contumeliouſly of the King, all men know that is not only uſual with him to revile and ſpeak ignominiouſly againſt the King privately, but alſo publickly in open Parliament: See the Speech of the Noble Peer, where 'tis ſaid, <hi>We want a Prince that we may Truſt;</hi> And in another paragraph of the ſame Speech, he bids the King to <hi>change His Principles, &amp;c.</hi> This un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civil Dialect is cuſtomary with <hi>Whigs</hi> in all Ages to Princes, as any Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian can tell, that has read the Life of <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of <hi>Scots,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vide, The Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> againſt the ſaid Queen.</note> whom <hi>Knocks</hi> the Miniſter called often Whore and <hi>Jezabel,</hi> and told her ſhe lyed a thouſand times to her face. And were not all the opprobriums in nature caſt upon that Royal Martyr King <hi>Charles</hi> I. before they brought His Royal Head to the Block? Certainly, if we do but look back into the Tranſactions of elapſed times, there is no Family under the Sun ought to deteſt the <hi>Whigs</hi> more, than the Royal Family of the <hi>Stuarts;</hi> for ſince the Reformation in theſe Kingdoms, that peſt of People have not only Rebelled, but alſo <hi>do facto</hi> murdered Three ſeveral Princes of the ſaid Royal Family, <hi>viz.</hi> Prince <hi>Henry</hi> King, <hi>James</hi>'s Father, Queen <hi>Mary</hi> before-mentioned, and the beſt of Kings, <hi>Charles</hi> the late Royal Martyr.</p>
            <p>Had the <hi>Whigs</hi> any grain of underſtanding, they would never believe that the Author of <note n="⋆" place="margin">The Earl of <hi>S.</hi> would have have <hi>Holland</hi> deſtroyed.</note> 
               <hi>Carthago delenda,</hi> was ever a <hi>True Protestant,</hi> but a <hi>Self intereſted States-mans;</hi> not ambitious to propagate <hi>True Religion,</hi> but avaritious to accumulate <hi>Riches and Honour to himſelf;</hi> and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh his unſatiable requeſts, God is the Cloak wherewith he ſhades his Monſtrous<note n="*" place="margin">Treaſon my be compared to a Monſter.</note>
               <hi>Hydra;</hi> And to attract a Popular Faction, of purpoſe to acquire his unreaſonable ends, he deludes the ignorant ſort of people with theſe bug-bear words, <hi>Religion, Property and Liberty are in a totte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſtate, if the Duke of</hi> Y. <hi>be not Excluded.</hi> 'Tis an old Saying, that <hi>quoties vis fallere, plebem ſinge Deum: If thou would'ſt deceive the Rabble, pretend Piety.</hi> Such is the ſubtilty of Crafty men in all Ages, to inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate into the minds of the Vulgar, either out of Diſcontent, or Self-inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, Rebellion and Treaſon, guilded over with the Bleſſed Name of<note n="*" place="margin">In nomine Domini incripit omne malum.</note>
               <hi>God.</hi> Theſe two Deified Pills, <hi>viz. Rebellion</hi> and <hi>Treaſon,</hi> exteriourly appearing ſpecious to their corporeal ſenſes, (though intrinſically ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomous) are unſenſibly ſwallow'd by the inconſiderate ſort of men, and in time infects and peſtifies their minds and bodies, and takes ſuch rooting in their Souls, until the intellectual parts are depraved, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing will ſtem them from revolution againſt the Government, but the panick fear of a Gallows, or being cut off by the Sword.</p>
            <p>But let the States-man animadvert, that there is 'no greater Glory, than to learn to ſubdue Ambition, when it floweth not from Juſtice; and to endeavour to preſerve our Conſcience and Honour inviolable, rather than acquire an Empire by ſiniſter means. Diadems won by ill ways, are not Characters of Glory to thoſe Heads that bear them,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:153714:12"/>but rather Wreaths of Infany, ſuch as are fixed on Varlets, and Thieves.</p>
            <p>And whereas 'tis alledged in the ſaid Pamphlet, that it is altogether incredible that ſuch a ſagacious and wiſe Peer as the Earl of <hi>Sh.</hi> could be Guilty of ſo great an Errour, as to make ſuch Raſcals as the Witneſſes are (for ſo the Pamphleteer calls them) privy to his Secrets: All men will deem the ſame as morally poſſible, as it was for His Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the Noble Lords in the Tower, to communicate their Secrets to ſuch Raſcals as <hi>Thom. D—ld</hi> and his Accomplices are. There is none but a ſilly crack-obrain'd <hi>Whig</hi> would publiſh ſuch a ſimple Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For, had he conſulted the Records of Parliament, and how the Noble Peer acknowledged his Errours upon his bended Knees, before the Bar of the Lords, in theſe words following, he would not juſtifie the Earl's Infalibility. Theſe are the words: <q>I do acknowledge, that my endeavouring to maintain that that the Parliament is Diſſolv'd, was an ill-adviſed action, for which I bed the Pardon of the King's Majeſty, and of this moſt Honourable Houſe And alſo I acknowledge, that my bringing of an <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> in the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> during this Seſſion, was an high violation of your Lordſhips Priviledges, and a great aggravation of my former Offence; <hi>for all which, I likewiſe moſt humbly beg the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of this moſt Honourable House.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Did not <hi>David</hi> err, that was a man after God's own heart? And alſo his Son <hi>Solomon,</hi> with whom God Covenanted, offer'd Victims to Idols, and falſe Gods: And ſhall the Phanaticks preſume to ſay, that he that was of the late Uſurpers Factions, contrary to his Allegiance, and the Honour of a true Gentleman, cannot err? 'Tis ſuch a Non-ſenſical Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that none but a ſtupid <hi>Whig</hi> would write the ſame, Beſides, has not the Noble Peer eaten of the King's Bread? was he not promoted to all the greateſt Preferments in <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Si ingratum d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xeris omnia d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xeris.</note> next to a Crowned Heard? And how he has remunerated His Majeſty, by his late <hi>Aſſociation</hi> againſt His Royal Perſon and Government, I leave to the conſideration of any ſober perſon.</p>
            <p>But ſuch is the blind Zeal of thoſe Factious Spawns of a Dunghil, that they will Canonine any man a Saint after their own impious man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, though never ſo wicked himſelf, that eſpouſes their Diabolical Intrigues.</p>
            <p>OF the Witneſſes that were ſuborned to appear againſt Mr. <hi>Heyns</hi> at <hi>Oxford,</hi> when <hi>College</hi> was tryed, take this ſhort Relation. Friſt of <hi>Betty Oliver,</hi> who has been a common Whore to ſeveral per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and eſpecially to one Mr. <hi>Cock</hi> that was a Priſonet in the <hi>Fleet;</hi> and after he relinquiſh'd her, ſhe had a Baſtard by one Mr. <hi>Briwingham</hi> a Red-Coat Souldier, now living in <hi>Tangier;</hi> afterwards ſhe lived in a Bawdy-houſe by <hi>Doctors Commons.</hi> If any queſtion the truth of this matter, let them repair to the <hi>Fleet-Priſon,</hi> where they may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed of moſt of the premiſſes, but ſeveral perſons there. This Whore was ſuborned to appear againſt <hi>Heyns</hi> at <hi>Oxford,</hi> by one Mr. <hi>Angel</hi> and the foreſaid <hi>Cock,</hi> the former having bought off the Pillory, he being convicted of Forgery, and ſeveral other Miſdemeanours, as <hi>Heyns</hi> will make appear, if occaſion requires. The later is the greatrſts <hi>Whig</hi> and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:153714:12"/>Rogue in Nature, and a Pimp to his own Daughter. He was a Priſoner in the <hi>Fleet</hi> for Cheating and Cozening; and his Chamber whilſt he remained there was always full of Pick-pockets, Whores and Bawds.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Edm. Ev—d,</hi> he was born in <hi>Ireland,</hi> his Father <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ilius populi,</hi> in pain <hi>Engliſh</hi> a Baſtard, and all his life-time a common Beggar, and a Plebean: <hi>Ev—d</hi> himſelf went into <hi>France</hi> when he was a Boy, and one Monſieur <hi>Gilow</hi> a Roniſh Prieſt, ſeeing him begging, like one of the Black-Guard-boys, in the ſtreets at <hi>Paris,</hi> he took him up for Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity-ſake, and kept him till the Beggar began to grow pround; but at laſt he was expelled out of the Colledge, for a miſdemeanour modeſty obliges me not to divulge: Afterwards Father <hi>Gaſcoine</hi> (Sir <hi>Thomas Gaſcoine</hi>'s Brother) having kept a Community in the Colledge of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tague,</hi> took him for Charity-ſake to wipe his Shoes; but committing ſome other Crime, he diſmiſs'd him; And afterwards he turned Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to the Abbot of <hi>Rheni,</hi> and remained in that ſtation for ſome time. One paſſage I muſt not omit of him, which was this: His Father being a common Beggar in <hi>Holland,</hi> (where he dyed) came to <hi>Paris</hi> to viſit his Son <hi>Edm. Ev—d,</hi> expecting ſome relief from him; but he ſeeing his Father in a moſt deſpicable condition, abſolutely renoune'd the old man to be his Father, notwithſtanding all his Countrey-men then at <hi>Paris</hi> knew the ſame poor man to be his Father; The old Beggar was fore'd to take his Staff and his Wallet, and mump all the way back to <hi>Holland</hi> again. He has this day a Wife at <hi>Paris,</hi> a Bakers Daughter in the University, but ſhe knows not what corner of the Univerſe he lives in. This Villain <hi>Ev—d,</hi> with <hi>A— S—</hi> and others, inſtructed the moſt part of thoſe Witneſſes that appeared againſt <hi>Heyns</hi> at <hi>Oxford,</hi> as ſome of the ſaid Witneſſes depoſed upon Oath before a Magiſtrate, ſince the Tryal of <hi>Stephen Colledge.</hi> After he left being Foot-man at <hi>Paris,</hi> he turned common Cheat; for he uſed to have a Port-mantle ſtuffed with ſome heavy mettal, and where-ever he took Lodgings, he made the folks believe his Port-mantle was full of Cold and Silver; and this courſe of life he led, till he cozen'd hundred; but a laſt he was ſeized upon at <hi>Pont-neufe,</hi> (in <hi>English New-bridge</hi>) in <hi>Paris,</hi> and carried before the Judge of Criminal matters, who committed him, in order to have him Hanged; for you muſt underſtand Cheats are hang'd by the Civil-Law; But his Countrey-men got him off, becauſe he was a ſtranger, and a <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick, and conveyed him out of Town, in order to his coming for <hi>England,</hi> where he has played ſeveral pranks, and ſtill will, until the Hang-man ſanctifies his Neck with a Rope.</p>
            <p>Another of theſe Raſcals that were ſuborned againſt <hi>Heyns,</hi> is one <hi>H— H—,</hi> a common Affidavit-fellow, as ſeveeral in Town will witneſs, when occaſion ſerves. This <hi>Hickman</hi> ſays, he heard <hi>Heyns</hi> through a Key-hole ſay to one Mrs. <hi>Scot, H—</hi>'s Lodger, it was <hi>Heyn's</hi> Trade to live by Swearing, (<hi>vide Colledg's</hi> Tryal, fol. 40.41.) where the Raſcal ſays in theſe words: <hi>I was at the Chamber-door, and loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked at the Key-hole, and he ſate at the window.</hi> When the Varlet was asked by the Judge how long ago it was he heard <hi>Heyns</hi> ſay ſo to Mrs. <hi>Scot?</hi> He replied, it was a year and a half before the ſaid Tryal of <hi>Colledge;</hi> whereas it will be made out, by the Gentlewomans Daughter, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:153714:13"/>more who live in Town, that Mrs. <hi>Scot</hi> parted from <hi>London</hi> the 25th. of <hi>July</hi> 1679. being the Feaſt of St. <hi>James,</hi> which was 2 yearrs the 25th. of <hi>July</hi> 1681. before the 17th. and 18th. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> when <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> was tryed at <hi>Oxford;</hi> ſo that <hi>A—S—</hi> and <hi>Ev—d</hi> did not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct him to a hairs breadth, having miſt half a year and above of the time he ſaw Mrs. <hi>Scot,</hi> as he pretended, in <hi>Heyns</hi>'s Company. This Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains Teſtimony againſt <hi>Heyns</hi> may be comparted to <hi>T—O—</hi>'s, who ſwore he ſaw His Royal Highneſs the Duke of <hi>York</hi> at Maſs, peeping through a Key-hole.</p>
            <p>Thus theſe Perjur'd Raſcals have endeavoured to ſtifle the Truth againſt <hi>Stephen Colledge,</hi> who was known by the very <hi>Whigs</hi> themſelves to be a man of very pernicious Principles againſt his Sovereign Prince, and the preſent Government.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:153714:13"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153714:14"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
